But first of all, people do not understand that you have to work it
लेकिन सबसे पहली बात तो यह है कि लोग यह नहीं समझते कि आपको इसे
through your heart and not\hthrough your brain.
दिल से करना है दिमाग से नहीं।
When we have to work out things through our brain, we try to develop\h\hour brain,
जब हमें अपने दिमाग से चीजों को निकालना होता है, तो हम अपने दिमाग को विकसित करने की कोशिश करते हैं,
isn’t it?
है ना?
By memorizing, by practising\hsomething,
याद करके, कुछ अभ्यास करके,
teaching our brain how to think, how to go this way that way.
हमारे मस्तिष्क को कैसे सोचना है, कैसे इस तरह से जाना है।
We try to train our brain.
हम अपने दिमाग को प्रशिक्षित करने की कोशिश करते हैं।
Now, we have to train our heart in Sahaja Yoga.
अब, हमें अपने हृदय को सहज योग में प्रशिक्षित करना है।
And to train our heart in Sahaja Yoga,
और हमारे हृदय को सहज योग में प्रशिक्षित करने
one has to\hknow, first of all,
के लिए, सबसे पहले यह जानना
that it is enveloped either by ego or by superego.
होगा कि यह या तो अहंकार से आच्छादित है या प्रतिअहंकार द्वारा।
The limbic area actually represents the heart.
लिम्बिक क्षेत्र वास्तव में हृदय का प्रतिनिधित्व करता है।
And if there is ego, heart will always be so-called,
और अगर अहंकार है, तो ह्रदय हमेशा तथाकथित रहेगा,
it will not be the real heart that\hwill be working, but it’s only mental,
वह वास्तविक ह्रदय नहीं होगा जो काम कर रहा होगा, बल्कि यह केवल मानसिक,
mental\hprojection.
मानसिक प्रक्षेपण है।
And you will feel that, “I’m doing\h\hit from my heart.”
और आपको लगेगा कि, "मैं इसे अपने दिल से कर रहा हूँ।"
But it’s not true.
लेकिन यह सच नहीं है।
Now then,\hsupposing, what should we do if we have ego?
अब मान लीजिए, अगर हमें अहंकार है तो हमें क्या करना चाहिए?
You might say, you should try to sort of tell yourself that, "That’s not good and this and that
आप कह सकते हैं, आपको अपने आप को यह बताने की कोशिश करनी चाहिए कि, "यह अच्छा नहीं है और यह और वह
and all\hkinds of mental suggestions"
और सभी प्रकार के मानसिक सुझाव"
or autosuggestions\hor this –
या स्वत: सुझाव या यह -
the way psychiatrists know that give you suggestions.
जिस तरह से मनोचिकित्सक जानते हैं कि आपको सुझाव देते हैं।
That’s again mental.
वह फिर से मानसिक है।
So,\hthat’s not the way it is going to work out.
तो, यह इस तरह से काम करने वाला नहीं है।
We must understand that for that what we have to do is to
हमें यह समझना होगा कि इसके लिए हमें क्या करना है
raise the left side and put it to the right side.
कि बायीं ओर को उठा कर दायीं ओर रखना है।
There’s no other way out.
कोई और रास्ता नहीं है।
You have to just work it out with your hands, your hands are working it out
आपको बस इसे अपने हाथों से काम करना है, आपके हाथ इसे काम कर रहे हैं
and not your brain.\hSo use your hands
न कि आपका दिमाग। तो अपने हाथों
and the methods of Sahaja Yoga.
और सहज योग के तरीकों का प्रयोग करें।
Now, everyone must have a regular sitting in the water
अब, प्रत्येक व्यक्ति को
every day, that’s important.
प्रतिदिन नियमित रूप से पानी में बैठना चाहिए, यह महत्वपूर्ण है।
Every morning you must do your meditation.
हर सुबह आपको अपना ध्यान अवश्य करना चाहिए।
You have to know that Sahaja Yoga is to be worked out, it‘s not to be thought out.
आपको यह जानना होगा कि सहज योग पर काम करना है, इसके बारे में सोचा नहीं जाना है।
You just cannot think about it. Whatever you may try to do through your thought,
आप इसके बारे में सोच ही नहीं सकते। आप अपने विचार के माध्यम से जो कुछ भी करने की कोशिश कर सकते हैं,
you cannot achieve any results in Sahaja Yoga. You\hhave to use your hands, you have to use your feet,
आप सहज योग में कोई परिणाम प्राप्त नहीं कर सकते। आपको अपने हाथों का उपयोग करना है, आपको अपने पैरों का उपयोग करना है,
\h\hyou have to soak your feet in the water because water is the ocean.
आपको अपने पैरों को पानी में भिगोना है क्योंकि पानी ही सागर है।
All these five chakras – or,\h\hsay, six chakras
ये सभी पांच चक्र - या, कहें, छह चक्र
which are — I say five because the…
जो हैं - मैं पांच कहता हूं क्योंकि ...
one is the Mooladhara Chakra, which is the seven
एक मूलाधार चक्र है, जो सात है
and the topmost is the brain.
और सबसे ऊपर मस्तिष्क है।
So, in between five chakras which are there —
तो, बीच में जो पांच चक्र हैं -
are to be handled fully
उन्हें पूरी तरह
with the\hidea that they are basically made of matter.
से इस विचार के साथ संभाला जाना चाहिए कि वे मूल रूप से पदार्थ से बने हैं।
And these five elements constitute
और ये पांच तत्व
the body of these chakras.
इन चक्रों के शरीर का निर्माण करते हैं।
Now, these chakras, if\hthey are to be corrected,
अब, इन चक्रों को, अगर इन्हें ठीक करना है,
we have to correct them by taking out all the problems of these chakras
तो हमें इन चक्रों की सभी समस्याओं को
into the elements from which they’re coming.
उन तत्वों में निकाल कर ठीक करना होगा, जिनसे ये आ रहे हैं।
For example, a person who is a very right-sided person,
उदाहरण के लिए, एक व्यक्ति जो बहुत ही दाहिनी ओर का व्यक्ति है,
so, he has to give a balance by the left-side.
इसलिए उसे बाईं ओर से एक संतुलन देना होगा।
Of course, raising with the hand is all right. But what about the element?
बेशक, हाथ से उठाना ठीक है। लेकिन तत्व का क्या?
Right-sided person has all the elements\hwhich give heat:
दाहिने हाथ वाले व्यक्ति में वे सभी तत्व होते हैं जो गर्मी देते हैं:
we can say, the light,
हम कह सकते हैं, प्रकाश,
we can say, the fire.
हम कह सकते हैं, अग्नि।
So, for people who are\hright-sided,
तो, जो लोग दाहिनी ओर हैं,
the light is not going to help much.
उनके लिए प्रकाश ज्यादा मदद नहीं करेगा।
Like, if you put the light before the photograph, and those who are ego-oriented people
जैसे, अगर आप फोटोग्राफ के सामने रोशनी डालते हैं, और जो लोग अहं-उन्मुख लोग हैं
— if you just use the light, it’s not going to work out.
- अगर आप सिर्फ रोशनी का इस्तेमाल करते हैं, तो यह काम नहीं करेगा।
So, what is going to work out is the Mother Earth
तो, जो काम करने जा रहा है वह है धरती माता
and the water element, which is cooling.
और जल तत्व, जो ठंडा कर रहा है।
Even ice\his very helpful to people who are right-sided.
यहां तक ​​कि बर्फ भी उन लोगों के लिए बहुत मददगार होती है जो दाएं तरफा होते हैं।
So, all cooling effects should be used for correcting your right-sidedness,
तो, सभी शीतलन प्रभावों का उपयोग आपकी दाईं ओर को ठीक करने के लिए किया जाना चाहिए,
so that you cool it down.
ताकि आप इसे ठंडा कर सकें।
Same about food.
भोजन के बारे में भी।
In food, those who are right-sided people should take to foods
खाने में जो लोग राइट साइड वाले
which are left-sided, that is carbohydrates, means they should become partly\hvegetarians,
हैं उन्हें लेफ्ट साइडेड खाना लेना चाहिए यानी कार्बोहायड्रेट यानी कि उन्हें आंशिक शाकाहारी
or quite a lot of vegetarians.
या काफी ज्यादा शाकाहारी बनना चाहिए।
And should eat things at the most like chicken,
और ज्यादा से ज्यादा चिकन जैसी चीजें खानी चाहिए,
but\hnot fishes, not seafoods because they are all hot.
लेकिन मछली नहीं, सी-फूड नहीं क्योंकि ये सभी गर्म होते हैं।
That’s how you treat your material side of your chakras.
इस तरह आप अपने चक्रों के भौतिक पक्ष का इलाज करते हैं।
Now, the left-sided people should use, again,
अब, वामपंथी लोगों को फिर से,
the "deepam" is the light or the fire
"दीपम" का उपयोग करना चाहिए, जो
to\hcorrect their left-side.
उनके बाएँ भाग को सही करने के लिए प्रकाश या अग्नि है।
Also, in food such people should take more to nitrogenous, means protein
साथ ही ऐसे लोगों को भोजन में नाइट्रोजेनस यानी प्रोटीन और ऐसे ही खाद्य पदार्थ अधिक लेने चाहिए
and\hfoods like that. They should take more proteins.
। उन्हें अधिक प्रोटीन लेना चाहिए।
Now, as far as Sahaja Yoga is concerned,
अब, जहाँ तक सहज योग का संबंध है,
the basic\hthing is Kundalini.
मूल चीज़ कुण्डलिनी है।
And the Kundalini, as I have told you, is the pure desire.
और कुंडलिनी, जैसा कि मैंने आपको बताया है, शुद्ध इच्छा है।
Again, listen\hto it carefully: pure desire.
फिर से इसे ध्यान से सुनें: शुद्ध इच्छा।
That means all other desires are impure.
अर्थात अन्य सभी इच्छाएं अशुद्ध हैं।
There’s only one pure\hdesire.
केवल एक शुद्ध इच्छा है।
And that is to be one with the Divine,
और वह है परमात्मा के साथ एक होना,
one with the Brahma, one with God — that’s the only pure desire.
ब्रह्म के साथ एक होना, ईश्वर के साथ एक होना - यही एकमात्र शुद्ध इच्छा है।
All other desires are impure.
बाकी सब कामनायें अशुद्ध हैं। इसलिए, अपने मन